Adolph Caspar Miller Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Adolph Caspar Miller Papers 1913-1947
MSS59261
Miller, Adolph Caspar, 1866-1953
10,000 items
34 containers
13.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Economist, educator, author, and member of the first Federal Reserve Board of Governors. Correspondence, memoranda, minutes, proceedings, writings, reports, speeches, notes, press releases, printed material, memorabilia, and other papers relating chiefly to Miller’s service as a member of the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, 1914-1936.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933--Correspondence.; Glass, Carter, 1858-1946--Correspondence.; Goldenweiser, E. A. (Emanuel Alexandrovich), 1883-1953--Correspondence.; Hamlin, Charles S. (Charles Sumner), 1861-1938--Correspondence.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964--Correspondence.; Lichtenstein, Walter, 1880-1964--Correspondence.; McAdoo, W. G. (William Gibbs), 1863-1941--Correspondence.; Miller, Adolph Caspar, 1866-1953.; Platt, Edmund, 1865-1939--Correspondence.; Riefler, Winfield W., 1897-1974--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945--Correspondence.; Stewart, Walter W., 1885-1958--Correspondence.; Strong, Benjamin, 1872-1928--Correspondence.; Warburg, Paul M. (Paul Moritz), 1868-1932--Correspondence.; Williams, John Skelton, 1865-1926--Correspondence.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924--Correspondence.
Organizations
Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System (U.S.); Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System (U.S.). Federal Advisory Council.; Open Market Investment Committee for the Federal Reserve System.; Panama-Pacific International Exposition (1915: San Francisco, Calif.)
Subjects
Banks and banking, International.; Banks and banking--United States.; Economic policy.; Finance--United States.; Franco-Prussian War, 1870-1871.; Industrial revolution.; Inflation (Finance); International economic relations.; International finance.; Monetary policy.
Places
Europe--Economic conditions.; France--History--Revolution, 1789-1799.; United States--Commerce.; United States--Economic conditions--To 1865.; United States--Economic policy--20th century.
Occupations
Authors.; Economists.; Educators.; Public officials.
Provenance
The papers of Adolph Caspar Miller, economist, educator, author, and member of the original Federal Reserve Board of Governors, were transferred to the Library of Congress from the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System in 1980.
Transfers
Some photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of the Adolph Caspar Miller Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Adolph Caspar Miller are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1866, Jan. 7 Born, San Francisco, Calif.
1887 A.B., University of California, Berkeley, Calif.
1888 A.M., Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1889 1890 Instructor of economics, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1890 1891 Assistant professor of history and politics, University of California, Berkeley, Calif.
1891 1892 Associate professor of political economy and finance, Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.
1895 Married Mary Sprague
1892 1902 Professor of finance, University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill.
1902 1913 Flood professor of economics and commerce, University of California, Berkeley, Calif.
1913 1914 Assistant to Secretary of the Interior Franklin K. Lane
1914 1936 Member, Board of Governors, Federal Reserve System
1921 1933 Member, Inter-American High Commission
1936 1953 Member, Library of Congress Trust Fund Board
1953, Feb. 11 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Adolph Caspar Miller (1866-1953), member of the original Federal Reserve Board of Governors, span the years 1913-1947 and relate specifically to the administration of monetary policy during Miller’s service with the Federal Reserve Board. The collection is organized as received by topic, name of person or organization, or by type of material.
The collection consists of internal correspondence and memoranda from individuals and other Federal Reserve banks; typescripts and handwritten copies of published articles, speeches, and notes relating to international and domestic banking and finance, drafts and final copies of minutes, reports, and proceedings of meetings and conferences of the Federal Reserve Board of Governors, agents, and chairmen from 1923 to 1936. There are also copies of correspondence and speeches and articles by several of Miller’s colleagues in academic and government service that relate to Federal Reserve policy. Among these items is an unpublished speech by Paul M. Warbug during his term as president of the Manhattan Corporation in 1930.
The collection includes internal correspondence and memoranda, internal documents and notes between Miller and members and staff of the Federal Reserve System, prominent individuals in banking and finance, and colleagues of Miller’s years as an academician. Correspondents include Carter Glass, E. A. Goldenweiser, Charles S. Hamlin, W. G. McAdoo Edmund Platt, Winfield W. Riefler, Walter Lichtenstein, Benjamin Strong, W. W. Stewart (director of the Federal Reserve Board’s Division of Analysis and Research), Paul M. Warburg, and John Skelton Williams.There are also letters and materials relating to the Panama Pacific International Exposition, of which Miller was chairman of government exhibits, 1914-1921.
Miller’s close relation with the White House is evidenced in the official and personal correspondence of the White, House, presidential letters, and individual correspondence files with Woodrow Wilson, Calvin Coolidge, Herbert Hoover, and Franklin D. Roosevelt. The correspondence with Hoover dates from his wartime service as food administrator, 1917-1919, as secretary of commerce under Presidents Warren G. Harding and Coolidge, 1921-1928, to his term as president, 1929-1933. This correspondence relates to international economic issues and policy such as economic recovery in Europe, inflation, foreign trade and the Commerce Department’s efforts to absorb the Agriculture Department’s function in foreign trade.
The papers also include correspondence, memoranda, minutes, reports, press releases and policy recommendations related to the Federal Advisory Council, dated 1916, 1920-1935, and the Open Market Investment Committee from 1923 to 1930. Parts of handwritten manuscripts and notes by Miller on subjects such as the Franco-German War, French Revolution, Industrial Revolution of 1837, new conditions favoring commerce, printed matter and miscellaneous memorabilia comprise the remainder of the collection.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged as received by topic, name of person or organization, or by type of material.
Container List
- Acceptance credits (Box 1)
- “C” miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Canadian Club of Ottawa (Box 1)
- Coolidge, Calvin (Box 1)
- Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y. (Box 1)
- Couzens, James (Box 1)
- Crissinger, Daniel R. (Box 1)
- Cross, Ira B. (Box 1)
- Cunningham, Edward H. (Box 1)
- Discount rates (Box 1)
- Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis (Box 1)
- Federal Reserve Bank of Richmond (Box 1)
- Federal Reserve Bank of San Francisco (Box 1)
- Glass, Carter (Box 1)
- Gold regulations (Box 1)
- Hamlin, Charles S., (3 folders) (Box 1)
- Hard, William. (Box 2)
- Harding, W. P. G. (Box 2)
- Harper & Brothers, (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Hayek, Frederick A. (Box 2)
- Hoover, Herbert (Box 2)
- Houston, David F (Box 2)
- McAdoo, W. G. (Box 3)
- Mellon, Andrew W. (Box 3)
- Miller, Adolph C., (5 folders) (Box 3)
- Mills, Ogden L. (Box 3)
- Minutes, Federal Reserve Board, excerpts (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous (2 folders) (Box 4)
- Mitchell, John R. (Box 4)
- New York Times (Box 4)
- Platt, Edmund (Box 4)
- Proclamation by the president, Mar. 1933 (Box 4)
- Quesnay, Pierre (Box 4)
- “R” miscellaneous (Box 4)
- Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Box 4)
- “S” miscellaneous (Box 4)
- Silver production (Box 4)
- Simpson, James (Box 4)
- Snyder, Carl (Box 4)
- Sprague, O. M. W. (Box 4)
- Statements during bank closing (Box 4)
- Sproule, William (Box 5)
- Strauss, Albert (Box 5)
- Strong, Benjamin (Box 5)
- Strong, James (Box 5)
- “T” miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Thomas, Elmer (Box 5)
- “V” miscellaneous (Box 5)
- “W” miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Warburg, Paul M. (Box 6)
- Warburg, Paul M. and James (Box 6)
- Warner, Ezra (Box 6)
- Westcott, Horace H. (Box 6)
- Wheeler, Benjamin Ide (Box 7)
- White House (Box 7)
  - Hoover, Herbert (Box 7)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Box 7)
- Williams, John Skelton (Box 7)
- Young, Roy A. (Box 7)
- Willis, H. Parker (Box 8)
- Wills, David C. (Box 8)
- Wilson, Woodrow (Box 8)
- Woodin, William H. (Box 8)
- “Y” miscellaneous (Box 8)
- Memoranda (Box 8)
  - 1917-1921, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - 1922-1929, (3 folders) (Box 9)
  - 1929-1935, (4 folders) (Box 10)
- Panama Pacific International Exposition, San Francisco, Calif. 1914-1915, (3 folders) (Box 11)
- Stewart, Walter W., (1 folder); (1 folders) (Box 12, Box 13)
- Goldenweiser, E. A. (Box 13)
  - 1926-1933, (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1933-1935, (2 folders) (Box 14)
- Federal Reserve Agents’ Conference (Box 14)
  - 1920-1932, (3 folders) (Box 14)
  - 1933-1935 (Box 15)
- Governors’ Conference (Box 15)
  - 1920-1926, (4 folders) (Box 15)
  - 1926-1936, (3 folders) (Box 16)
- Joint Conference of Governors and Chairmen of Federal Reserve Banks, 1920-1922, (2 folders) (Box 16)
- Conference Committee report, HR7837, 1913 (Box 16)
- Federal Advisory Council, (3 folders) (Box 17)
- Open Market Investment Committee, 1923-1930, (2 folders); (5 folders); (1 folders) (Box 17, Box 18, Box 19)
- Federal Reserve policy, 1921, (2 folders) (Box 19)
- Committee on Branch, Group and Chain Banking (Box 19)
- Committee on Bank Reserves (Box 20)
- Speeches, writings, and notes, (4 folders); (2 folders) (Box 20, Box 21)
- Currency conditions in India, (3 folders) (Box 21)
- Federal Reserve charts (Box 21)
- Glass Committee hearings, (2 folders) (Box 22)
- Speeches, writings, and notes, (3 folders) (Box 22)
- Federal Reserve Act, 1916-1917, 1930-1939 (Box 23)
- Banking Act, 1935 (Box 23)
- Discount rates (Box 24)
- Federal Advisory Council, 1918-1919 (Box 24)
- Speeches, writing, and notes, (3 folders); (1 folder) (Box 24, Box 25)
- Federal Reserve Banks (Box 25)
  - Annual report, 1923, (4 folders) (Box 25)
  - Annual report data for 1925 (Box 26)
  - Chairmen and Federal Reserve agents, 1934 (Box 26)
  - Comptroller of the Currency, 1933 (Box 26)
  - Control of speculative credit (Box 26)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1935 (Box 26)
  - Printed matter (Box 26)
  - Terms of Members of Federal Reserve Board (Box 26)
- Speeches, writings and notes, (1 folder); (7 folders); (4 folders); (3 folders) (Box 26, Box 27, Box 28, Box 29)
- Presidential letters, 1913-1914, 1931-1939 (Box 29)
- Appointment to Federal Reserve Board, 1914, 1933-1941 (Box 29)
- Speeches, writings, and notes, (3 folders) (Box 30)
- Lane, Franklin (Box 30)
- Passports (Box 30)
- Mezes, Sidney E. (Box 30)
- James, George (Box 30)
- Sévres busts of American statesmen, 1922-1923 (Box 30)
- Finlandia material, 1927, 1934-1935 (Box 30)
- Miscellaneous letters, 1917-1921, 1928-1937 (Box 30)
- Chase National Bank (Box 31)
- Banking Act of 1935 (Box 31)
- The credit situation, 1925-1926 (Box 31)
- Committee on Recent Economic Changes, 1927-1928 (Box 31)
- Speeches, writings, and notes, (3 folders); (5 folders); (4 folders) (Box 31, Box 32, Box 33)
- Banking studies, 1940, (4 vols.) (Box 34)